there is a new very cool and useful feature on
the GrandMA3 software called recast. GrandMA3
recast is a new way of being able to change your
existing programming on your show file and you can
find it in the settings of all your presets. And
you might think that this is not very important
but i think that this feature will make your
life a lot easier as a GrandMA3 programmer
especially if you are touring your show and
cloning new fixtures into your show all the time
in this episode of our GrandMA3
tutorial i will show you how it works
and i'll try to explain why i think it's so
groundbreaking that ma lighting incorporated this
feature into the GrandMA3 software so let's get
into it to show you how recast works i've set up
a new view here on the GrandMA3 on pc software
and i'm going to show you two examples of the
different functionalities so first of all we have
our new view here i have a playback window up here
i have my 3d window up here i have my sequence
down here and i have a fixture sheet over here
so let's take all our wipers and put them into
a color of some sort let's say we need them in
red so we turn them on at full and we put them
in some sort of position right here there we go
we can store this as a preset as we've done many
times before in this tutorial series but this time
i've chosen an all preset and all preset doesn't
filter down the functionality as you would see
position do position only stores the position
values gobo only stores gobo values and so on
all preset stores all values so whatever you have
active is going to be stored into the all preset
but this time i'm just going to clear out because
i made a small mistake we turn on all the vipers
we turn them on at full and we put them in the
position we talked about before like this let's
store this into there we go into a sequence up
here so if we clear this one and say go to this
one we have our preset so let's give it a color we
take all our wipers again and we put them in red
like this there we go and let's store this in
our all preset now our old preset only contains
color information so if i choose all my
vipers and put them into the red color
i can store them in our sequence here in
cue number one so if we clear this one
they will stay red so now i want to add some
zoom information to this just as an example
normally if i order if i put zoom information
or any other value into this it's not going to
affect the programming at all so let's try
this let's go to focus let's take the zoom
all the way down to zero and let's store this into
our preset right here you'll see when i clear here
they go back to whatever they were doing because
the preset i programmed with i choose i chose all
my vipers put them in red and this preset at that
time only contained the red information i stored
this in my sequence up here and now the problem
is that the sequence now only looks at the color
but the really really cool thing is you can now go
down here and say edit settings and you can find
this button down here saying recast preset if
i recast and i clear you will see now the value
has changed for the sequence number one and it
now contains the zoom information and the color
information as well and that is a really cool
thing to do i can see this functionality being
really really useful if you are like touring
a show and you are cloning from one fixture
type to another fixture type and say for
instance you have programmed your entire show
on cmy colors or rgb colors and then the figure
you're cloning to only has static colors and you
want to change all your programming so it contains
the right colors and you want to be a little bit
more in charge of how the cloning process is
going to be so this is one of the use cases
where i can really see it being helpful so let's
try something different let's say we choose all
our vipers again we take the color out let's just
put it in maybe just put it in yellow and then we
add a gobo to it so now it has a gobo if we store
this into the preset here and we say overwrite
it's going to remove all the information that
it had previously it had some zoom information
and it had some color information right now we
changed the color and we didn't store any zoom
information and we put a gobo in start that as
well so if i clear out here it's going to go
back to only the color preset we used before the
reason why it goes back to the color is the color
it already knew the color value so we could
change the color we just couldn't change the
gobo and the gobo disappeared so if i go into
our settings right now and recast our preset
and we clear you can see the zoom information
disappeared because we removed it from this preset
and it added the gobo information and it changed
the color information so that's another way of
using the recast if you like this feature and
see the value in it i'm going to show you a much
easier way to recast multiple presets at the same
time so be sure to stick around to the end of this
video so you don't miss it and if you enjoy this
video and find it useful be sure to give it a like
that's gonna help my channel to spread out to more
people on youtube. Liking videos is a great and
free way to support any youtube channel and please
leave a comment below if you have any questions
regarding GrandMA3 or suggestions for future
topics we could cover in this tutorial series.
i'd love to help you in any way i can. And if
you are interested in GrandMA3 hardware i
have some links in the description for all kinds
of different pieces of GrandMA3 hardware for a
better overview of all the different models i have
a special landing page with a lot of different
GrandMA3 consoles you can also find this link
in the description. And a small disclaimer the,
links in the description are all affiliate links
and that means if you decide to purchase some of
the products i will receive a small commission
on the sale. So with that out of the way let's
continue learning GrandMA3 recast recasting
your presets through the settings menu is fine but
we need a faster way of doing it so let's just
set it up we take all our vipers we put them
in some sort of strobie mode here let's store
this into our preset right here and let's clear
once again it stops strobing because it's only
looking at the color so if we want to recast
that in a faster way we just use the command
line we say recast we say preset we say 21.37
and the reason why we call it 21 is you can see
our all preset is preset 21 as our gobo is 3 our
focus is 6 and so on so now we want to recast
preset 21.37 because that's the preset number
here if i press ok to that it's going to recast it
through the command line another cool way we can
do that is copy this information here we make
a new macro we insert a new macro line and we
paste our recast preset in as we just wrote
there we go and we can rename this one
re -cast there we go and then we clear out
here and then let's say we want to remove
the global information we take our vipers
maybe we double click on this one and we say
remove and we store this in our preset we clear
and now we can simply press the macro we just made
and it stops so recasting presets is really really
cool you can recast as we did here we recasted
preset 21.37 you can recast multiple presets
here 37 through uh if we said through 500 it
would recast all the presets in that range so this
is how recast works GrandMA3 programming is kind
of fun and remember that we are still in the very
early stages of the software i'm sure that GrandMA3
software will evolve a lot over the next few
years just like the early days of the GrandMA2
software be sure to give this video a like so
it can spread out to more people and subscribe to
the channel if you don't want to miss any future
episodes and if you're on the journey of learning
GrandMA3 from scratch i highly suggest that you
watch this next video you can see on your screen
right now in this video i'll show you some other
cool features of the GrandMA3 software i try to
release one new video per week so please come back
if you want to continue learning GrandMA3
i hope to see you on the channel again sometime
in the future and until then happy programming